Pinak Kapalay

Survey No. 13/1, Radhika Bldg., Lakshmi Nagar, Balewadi, Pune

Pin: 411045

Tel: +91 9158266287

Email: pinak.kapalay@gmail.com

SUMMARY

An M. Tech. (Automobile Engineering) from **NIT Warangal** with 4 years of work experience in Core Industry as well as Training. Exceptional Analytical and Logical skills, Excellent at communication and presentations. Good at statistics and interpretation. A Quick learner, Self Motivated and Firm believer in Team Work. Open to relocating. Keen on exploring opportunities in Data Science. Passionate about playing Badminton.

EDUCATION

2018 Imarticus Learning Pune, India

• Data Science Prodegree course

- » Statistical Analysis System (SAS).
- » R Language (Models including Logistic Regression, Decision Tree, Random Forest)
- » Python (Models including Logistic Regression, Decision Tree, Random Forest, SVM)

Achievements: Batch topper of the DSP course, achieved Certificate of Excellence.

2011-2013	National Institute of Technology (NIT), Warangal Master in Technology in Automobile Engineering (7.16 Pointer)	Warangal, India
2006 - 2010	St. Vincent Pallotti Colg of Engineering and Technology Bachelors in Engineering in Mechanical Engineering (64 %)	Nagpur,India
2004- 2006	Bhavan's B.P. Vidya Mandir (BVM) H.S.C (66.67 %)	Nagpur, India
2004	Bhavan's B.P. Vidya Mandir (BVM) S.S.C (85.2 %)	Nagpur, India

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming

- R Hands on R programming and statistical computing using various models.
- **Python** Hands on Python programming and statistical model building and computing.

Statistical Analysis & Data Analytics [Strategic Thinking. Modeling. Analytics]

- Data Cleansing
- Data Manipulation
- Feature Engineering

- Predictive AnalyticsHypothesis Testing
- Descriptive Statistics
- Exploratory Analysis

Machine Learning:

- Linear Regression
- Logistic Regression
- Decision Tree

- Random Forest
- Support Vector Machine
- Time Series

Mechanical Softwares:

- Proficient in CATIA V5. A certified course at Astral Informatics Pvt. Ltd.
- Proficient in ANSYS 14.5. A certified course at Astral Informatics Pvt. Ltd.

PROJECTS in DATA SCIENCE

- Worked on two live Projects given to the Institute by their existing client. Hands on Experience on R Programming and Python. Models employed included Logistic Regression, Support Vector Machines and Decision Tree.
- Currently working on a Live industrial Project as a Freelance Data Analyst. Working on Python Programming.

For miscellaneous other works from various Data Websites:

Rpubs Profile : https://rpubs.com/Pinak18
Github Profile : https://github.com/Pinak18

DETAILS OF THE DATA SCIENCE PROJECTS WORKED ON:

- Predictions of Bad Loans: This project included study, visualization and analysis of the past data provided by the client and build a model which would predict, for which customer, the loan needs to be passed. Needed to build a model which would predict the potential defaulters, based on the previous data. Employed Logistic Regression, Support vector machine and Random forest to build a high accuracy best fit model. Modelling was done using Python.
- Prediction of Employee Attrition: The project consisted of studying the previous data, analyzing it and predicting the employees most likely to switch or resign from the client. Worked on the data with Support Vector Machine, Random Forest, Principal Component Analysis and employed technique of feature engineering to arrive at the best model. Coding done using R programming. (Oct 2018 Feb 2019)
- Prediction of Loan Early Repayment (Currently Working): The project includes analysis of the client data and building a model to predict the potential customers who would foreclose their loan account. Prediction of Foreclosure is important as it costs dearly to the financial firm. Modelling done using Random Forest, Logistic Regression and K-nearest Neighbours algorithms. Programming done in Python. (Feb 2019 Present)
- Prediction of effect of changing parameters on Exhaust (Currently Working): This project comprises of
 working with the past data provided by the client and his experimental data. Prediction of the effect of change
 in parameters of engine on the exhaust and comparing it to the past data is required. General analysis and
 linear regression algorithms are being used. Programming done using R language. (Mar 2019 Present)
- **Performance Analysis of Students:** This project included working on the data collected from an educational institute, analyze it and predict which of the students lag in academics and draw a conclusion based on that. Even aid the institution in increasing the student performance using the same analysis.

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Post- Graduation:

• <u>Title</u>:"A combined analysis of the performance and emissions of a diesel engine using blends of Mahua Oil Methyl Ester (MOME) subjected to variation in the Injector opening pressure."

WORK EXPERIENCE: 3 Years 10 Months

March 2018- Present: Data Scientist

Role: Data Scientist and Analyst.

Process: Currently working on a live industrial Project.

Oct 2018- Present: Sinhgad Institute of Technology and Science, Narhe

Role: Assistant Professor

Process: Training students in Mechanical engineering subjects.

Feb 2016- Jun 2018: SKN Sinhgad Institute of Technology and Science, Lonavla

Role: Assistant Professor

Process: Training students in Mechanical engineering subjects.

Achievements:

• Received a 100% student feedback for training in Strength of Materials.

Feb 2014- Oct 2015: CATIA V5 Freelance Trainer

Role: CATIA V5 Trainer.

Process: Training students in CATIA V5 Design Software.

Nov 2013- Jan 2014: Miltech Industries Pvt. Ltd.

Role: Graduate Engineering Trainee.

Process: Supervising working of a complete shift and facilitate its smooth working.

Responsibilities:

- Responsible for Delivering the batch of products in stipulated time.
- Making sure, no Production related issue hampers the committed delivery date to the client.

EXTRA CURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

- Represented NIT Warangal for Inter University South Zone and Compete 2013 Inter NIT badminton tournament.
- > Runners up in intercollegiate Basketball tournament.
- > Runners up in intercollegiate skit competition.
- Presented paper on topic "SPACE TIME THRILLS".

PERSONAL DETAILS

Name : PINAK PRAMOD KAPALAY

Nationality : Indian Marital Status : Single

Date of Birth : 18/ 03/ 1988

Gender : Male

Languages Known : English, Hindi, and Marathi.

Permanent Address : Flat No. S/2, Manohar Jyoti Apartments, S.E. Railway Colony,

Ranapratap Nagar, Nagpur-440022